### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ houstonwehaveaproblem (LinkedIn)

# Top Skills

Entrepreneurship Start-ups Innovation

## Languages

French (Native or Bilingual)
English (Full Professional)

### Honors-Awards

IBD Innovation by Design Awards 2016

101Projets Laureate - Raised 25K € in One Minute Pitch Contest from TOP3 French Business Angels

3rd prize (on 17 candidates) on Innovative Feature Challenge - Night Of Code 2013

1st prize (on 61 candidates) on Creativity Challenge with HTML5 -Night of Code 2013

# SOFIANE B.

Principal Engineer & Tech Lead & Senior Software Engineer Paris, Île-de-France, France

# Summary

I turn bold ideas real. With a blend of technology know-hows, wide and sharp technical skills and project building experience with limited team/resources, I'm able to give life to a product/project and bring it to market with success.

# Experience

Tribe App

Founding Backend Engineer -- Social, Video Streaming, Al January 2016 - Present (8 years 7 months)

Région de la baie de San Francisco, États-Unis

- Tribe Video messaging app (now part of Twitter Periscope).
- Raise \$3M from Sequoia Capital.
- Build a high scalability backend infrastructure.

Tribe uses natural language processing to recognize spoken words and put digital words on the video

Handling millions of requests per day with confidence

Designed and built a microservice-based API with graphQL endpoint using NodeJS, Docker, Redis, MySQL, Google Datastore

Managed and deployed containers on Google Cloud Platform with Kubernetes and tuning for high scalability

Built a MQTT High Scale Cluster with Docker

Designed & Built a realtime GameServer for thousands of concurrent players

Realtime

Security

Video Compression ffmpeg/gstreamer

**Functional Reactive Programming** 

Domain Design Driven

Behaviour Driven Development

Node.js

C++ / rxcpp

leveldb

Golang

**AWS Fargate** 

#### eFounders

Lead Backend Engineer (Spendesk) -- FinTech and Cyber Security November 2015 - April 2016 (6 months)

Région de Paris, France

Lead Backend Engineer "Spendesk" FinTech SaaS Product Distributed NodeJS infrastructure on AWS

### PartyBay

Founder

February 2014 - October 2015 (1 year 9 months)

Région de Paris, France

- Raised 25K€ from French BA: Xavier Niel, Marc Simoncini, JAG
- Built and led a cross-functional 7-member team to develop a complete event planning platform with low budget, fast iterations, and a short period of time
- Designed a RESTful API & implemented Oauth 2.0 server (RFC 6749) + iOS SDK
- Developed a native and fluid iOS app in Swift connected to a RESTful API backend
- DevOps: Created complex dev env with Puppet (Ruby) and CI env with Jenkins and Sonar

#### Substantiel

Full-Stack Engineer & Growth Hacker May 2013 - October 2013 (6 months)

• Increased ads revenue by 1000% (from 90€/day to 900€/day) in 2 months by developing an ads placement auto testing tool based on CPC (CASHFLOW) using Adwords and Critéo APIs

# Education

#### **ECE Paris**

Master's Degree, Computer and Information Sciences / minor Entrepreneurship · (2010 - 2015)

**Dublin Business School** 

Summer Business Program, Product Design / Marketing · (2013 - 2014)

Concordia University

Engineer's Degree, Computer Science Engineering · (2012 - 2013)

University of California, Irvine

Business English & Marketing · (2011 - 2012)